Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
James Britton papers
- Diaries, 1918-1935, Series 4:; (Box 1-2; 1.5 linear feet)
  - Diaries, 1918-1935, Subseries 4.1:
    - James Britton's Draft Index to Diaries, XXV-XL, circa 1920s, (not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - James Britton's Final Index to Diaries, XXV-XL, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 1, 1925 January-February, June (Box 1, Folder 37)
      (discusses George Bellows and Childe Hassam exhibiting at Macbeth Galleries; the death of George Bellows; visits Dwight William and Mrs. Tryon in New York Ciry, discusses the Freer Gallery of Art at length; travels to Kraushaar Galleries to see paintings by Sloan and Bellows.)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 2, 1925 February-March (Box 1, Folder 38)
      (Britton participates in the First Exhibition of the Charter Members of the New Society of American Artists; list of members of the New York Portrait Society; exhibition at Babcock Galleries in April; New Society of Artists Committee meeting; list of portraits by year and sitter)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 3, 1925 March-April (Box 1, Folder 39)
      (attends a meeting of the New Society of American Artists at the studio of George Lobens with George Pease Ennis, Bruce Crane of the Salmagundi Club who nominate Ernest Blumenschein to join the committee; discusses Kyokei Inukai; discusses Babcock Galleries' poor treatment of artists; meets Milton Avery; talks of Opus)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 4, 1925 October-1926 March (Box 1, Folder 40)
      (travels to Knoedler's and meets Jim Weiland; goes to Metropolitan Museum of Art with son Jerome; attends a George Bellows memorial exhibition; descrition of the New Britain Institute with a list of artists represented; visits James Goodwin McManus's studio; discusses "The Chess Players" by Robert Bolling Brandegee; talks with Frank Rehn; sees Frederick Detweiller; list of pictures over which to "make a big ex" (35); visits Louis Comfort Tiffany; list of portraits by others of which Britton wanted copies for inspiration and admiration (90-91) )
    - Miscellaneous Volume 5, circa 1925 October-1926 May (Box 1, Folder 41)
      (discusses industry versus art in America; a draft of "Art and New Business"; list of works of art in Waterbury, CT by Britton; second annual exhibition of the New Society of American Artists; discusses the Connecticut Academy; the relationship between painting and writing)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 6, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      (consists of notes on Copley and Haydn and Beethoven; list of Copley portraits of British and Americans painted in England; notes on Copley at the Royal Academy)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 7, 1926 July-1928 January (Box 1, Folder 43)
      ("notes on the literature of American Art"; has an exhibition at M. Knoedler and Co. Galleries; information about his Copley book; notes on Pyle and Stewart; suggests creating a Mark Twain group portrait; a list of books by W.M. Howells; list of woodcuts by Britton organized by date; notes on Mozart, Haydn and Beethoven; visits Kraushaar Galleries and the Morgan Museum; visits with Norwegian artist Lars Thorsen; discusses the pub culture of Hartford, CT; list of woodcuts by Walter Eitel; talks with Frank Gay of the Wadsworth Athenaeum; talks of Borglum and Caffin in Hartford reminisences)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 8, 1928 February-1929 October (Box 1, Folder 44)
      (sells book on Copley; visits Walter Eitel and Frederick Detweiller; list of portraits painted by Hartford artists or of Hartford sitters; list of paintings--various; a draft of a letter to Edwin Valentine Mitchell and one to F. Detweiller; Mr. Bartlet, an engraver visits; gives an interview for The Republican with Miss Cullen; a list of books with Howell's; goes to Morgan Museum and cannot find his portrait of Charles Flagg; talks of his father Captain J. Britton; invited to exhibit at the Women's Club of Hartford with Maud Monnier--includes a list of paintings possible for exhibition; commentary on Hartford Philharmonic Orchestra; discusses "The Banquet of the Presidents" and his intent for the painting)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 9, 1929 December-1931 March (Box 1, Folder 45)
      (talks with Father Andrew Kelly; lists of sales from the Women's Club Art Committee exhibitiion wiht a description of the event; talks of his portrait of Inukai; complaints of those considered "Rich Hartford"; visits Morgan Museum exhibitions including French, Italian, and Mexican paintings; draft of "The Battle of American Art" (53); sees an exhibition of Higgins etchings; a draft of a letter to Phillip Hardy; list of ideas for "Modern Life" series; two lists of paintings: for patrons in Hartford and of subjects residing in Hartford or the vicinity; a list of old paintings received from storage; comment on New York Tribune announcing the publication of the Copley book; a list of paintings to exhibit at Women's Club in November; pressures Morgan Museum for more paintings to cover all American Art movements and time periods; list of visitors to visit the Women's Club exhibition; a list of portraits for Britton to see or write about; comments on business during the depression)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 10, 1931 March-August (Box 1, Folder 46)
      (list of visitors to the Women's Club exhibtion, November 3, 1930; draft of a letter to Charles A Goodwin wiht a list of artists that should be represented at the Wadsworth Athenaeum; discusses Max Weber portrait; describes how he varnishes his paintings; a sketch of his studio space; essays entitled "Men's Mission" and "Women's Mission"; talks of Connecticut Shore Art Guild summer exhibition and a list of possible exhibtions; a price list from an exhibtion at Folsom Gallery in New York City)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 11, 1931 September-1932 April (Box 1, Folder 47)
      (essay entitled "Dialog in a Portrait Painter's Studio"; contains an essay by Caroline Britton concerning Christian Science and prayer of Man and God; lists of portraits based on the age of the painting; commentary on European versus American artists; begins to discuss his health problems; a review of Jane Eyre and Shirley; a list of sales to Father Kelly; death of Maud Monnier; writes for the catalog for the Edith Stevens memorial exhibition; visit from Max and Mrs. Bengs; describes the role of Hartford's Cheney family in Prohibition; expresses frustration over having one of his woodcuts produced without permission; old friend Russel Northman commits suicide)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 12, 1932 May-October (Box 1, Folder 48)
      (vivid commentary on the effect of the Depression on the Britton family and the country in general; talks of Guy Pene du Bois; a critique of the American Intelligensia and their lack of focus on American Art(12); talks of Socialism in America at length-20; talks of Edith Stevens and her suicide; describes legal troubles and that a judge ruled his paintings as collateral; comments on suicide during Depression; discusses Father Kelly's art collection and his new O'Keefe works; a description of the Presidents within "The Presidents Banquet"; discusses the election of Franklin Roosevelt; gives commentary on Irish politics; having difficulty with his wife; a list of paintings with Father Kelly; discusses falling out with Father Kelly because Britton will not convert to Catholicism)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 13, 1932 November-1933 February (Box 2, Folder 1)
      (visit from Henry Nord; discusses Roosevelt's election; talks of problems with his relationships with Father Kelly and wife, Caroline; reflections on the art scene in New York City-57; list of data on "The Presidents Banquet"; death of Tom Brabazon; looting and petty theivery during the Depression)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 14, 1933 February-March (Box 2, Folder 2)
      (contains many details of the poor economic conditions and the effect on society and his own familial relationships; Socialist and Communist activities of his wife; discusses attempted shooting of Roosevelt in Florida; visit from Tom Supples, a baseball player; financial conditions of museums in Hartford; discusses the Beer Bill and the end of Prohibition and the Bank Holiday; recollections of Ida Tarbell; a list of paintings lost-93)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 15, 1933 April-May (Box 2, Folder 3)
      (many notes on classical music and composers; discussion of the new beer after Prohibition; suffers from ill health and talks of the activities of his children; visits from the son of E.C. Potter, sculptor)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 16, 1933 May-July (Box 2, Folder 4)
      (contains many sketches; discusses Civil War photography; a sketch of a surgery done by his brother-in-law Dr. Boucher; list of paintings; discusses the job market for post-high school students; list of paintings owned by Father Kelly; descriptions of landscape paintings and comments on painting over old canvases-54; list of paintings owned by Walter Eitel and E.V. Mitchell)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 17, 1933 July-August (Box 2, Folder 5)
      (discusses article about Father Kelly's art collection in The Transcript; essay "Modernism Blows Up"; talks of the quality of paper available in America-9; concern with his copyright over images; anger of the patronage of Father Kelly; observations on New York City and the effects of Prohibition; Knights of Columbus activities in Connecticut)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 18, 1933 August (Box 2, Folder 6)
      (notes on Copley's "Death of Chatham"; essay "New Art Modernism"; reminisences of Hartford Art Institute and Art League; list of American portraits for potential exhibition; list of Copley reproductions owned by Britton; proposal for a political party called The Heroes-51; draft of a letter to the Hartford Courant concerning "Cure d'Ars")
    - Miscellaneous Volume 19, 1933 September-October (Box 2, Folder 7)
      (comments on children's activities and schooling; copies music of Beethoven and Haydn; talks of Roosevelt's presidency; discusses having prints made from engravings with Father Kelly)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 20, 1933 October-November (Box 2, Folder 8)
      (death of George Luks; Tom Spellacy as the mayor of Hartford; futher discusses Socialist and Libertine activities of Caroline)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 21, 1933 December (Box 2, Folder 9)
      (Father Kelly holds exhibition at the Andrea Art Gallery in Hartford; writes on the difference between professional and amateur artists; copy of a letter to Father Kelly; reelection of President Roosevelt; memo "Petition of Artist for a Break")
    - Miscellaneous Volume 22, 1934 January-February (Box 2, Folder 10)
      (discusses political and social situations in Germany; talks about Katherine Hepburn's family in Connecticut; letter to Father Kelly concerning prices of works of art)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 23, 1934 March-May (Box 2, Folder 11)
      (Caroline elected as an honorary member to the local labor union of textile workers; talks of Civil Works Administration and government sponsored art; discusses Juliana Force closing Whitney Museum for fear of violance; moves in with sister due to family troubles; issues with Father Kelly's patronage; Britton family is evicted and forced to find a new place to live)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 24, 1934 May-June (Box 2, Folder 12)
      (draft of a letter to Father Kelly; outlines his problems with Father Kelly-23; discusses racial tension in the South; death of Frank B. Gay; sketches; discussion of "The Presidents Banquet")
    - Miscellaneous Volume 25, 1934 July (Box 2, Folder 13)
      (mostly sketches and artworks including color)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 26, 1934 August-September (Box 2, Folder 14)
      (troubles with his family concerning his disagreement with wife's affiliation with labor unions; Jerome has an exhibition; Mr. Monnier dies; Caroline urges workers of Cheney Mills to join labor unions; draft of a letter to Tom Spellacy)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 27, 1934 September-December (Box 2, Folder 15)
      (this diary was recycled twice and is therefore difficult to read--it was used by Jerome as a school book, by Britton in 1930, then Britton returned to it in 1934; essays from 1930 "Everybody to Work" "Untitled Play"; essay from 1934 "Truce and the Pope"; concerning Senator John Blackwell; sketch of paintings-113)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 28, 1935 January-February (Box 2, Folder 16)
      (memoranda concerning prints for publication; list of possible purchasers of Roosevelt painting; sketches; list of paintings to be duplicated or printed; discussion of Huey Long)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 29, 1934 February-July (Box 2, Folder 17)
      (discusses Roosevelt's cabinet and Huey Long; draft of letters to Detweiller; death of Augustus Lukeman, sculptor; sketches; talks of the Andrea Art Guild turning into a Catholic lending library; recalls time spent with Cecilia Beaux in 1909)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 30, 1934 July-December (Box 2, Folder 18)
      (moves into sister's home due to health probelms; list of people in the Connecticut State Offices along with salaries and locations; sketches; list of potential portrait subjects and landscapes)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 31, 1935 January-February (Box 2, Folder 19)
      (talks of "foreign policy" of the Morgan Museum; letter by Joanna Boucher for school; letter to Senator Blackwell; sketches; inscriptions of books on composers; proposal for a Copley Society in Connecticut; form letter for solicitation of Roosevelt painting)
    - Miscellaneous Volume 32, 1935 February-July (Box 2, Folder 20)
      (list of members of the Copley Society of America, 1908; sketches; list of trustees and members of the Museum Arts Committee; draft of letter to the editor of the Herald addressed to Democrats)
  - James Britton's Notebooks of Diary Excerpts, 1919-1934, Subseries 4.2:
    James Britton created ten volumes of excerpts from his diary, presumably those that he felt were the most significant.
    - Volume 1, 1918-1919 January (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Volume 2, 1919 January-March (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Volume 3, 1919 March-July (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Volume 4, 1919 July-1920 February (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Volume 5, 1920 March-September (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Volume 6, 1920 September-1921 April (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Volume 7, 1921 April-1923 February (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Volume 8, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Volume 9, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Volume 10, 1934 August-November (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1910s-1935, Series 5:; (Boxes 2-3; 0.4 linear feet)
  Writings and notes by Britton include a handwritten and incomplete typescript of an autobiography, writings for his publication Opus, draft writings for his book, Artists of America, drafts of "Copley, Modern Old Master", writings about Charles Noel Flagg, and essays about art and classical music, and plays. There are also three notebooks and notes. There are also writings by Duncan Scott Kent and Blackfield.
  Writings and Notes are arranged into 2 subseries:
  Subseries 5.1: Writings By James Britton, circa 1910s-1935
  Subseries 5.2: Writings By Others, circa 1910s-circa 1928
  - Writings by James Britton, circa 1910s-1935, Subseries 5.1:
    - Autobiography, circa 1930s, (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 31-35)
    - Autobiography, typescript, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - "American Portraits," circa 1920s (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - "Art Museum Ethics," circa 1920s (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - "Art-Position of America," circa 1920s (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - "Art-Opus 8," circa 1924 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - "Artists of America, Pt 1," circa 1926 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Artists of America, Pt 2," circa 1926 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - "Artists of America, Pt 2," draft, circa 1926 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - "Copley, Modern Old Master," circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - "Copley, Modern Old Master," draft, circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Modern Art," circa 1910s (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - "No Czar for Artists," circa 1920s (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Painting of String Quartet," circa 1910s (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - "Painter's Wife," circa 1920s (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Concerning Charles Noel Flagg, 1925 August (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous, Concerning Art, 1925, circa 1910s (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "Haydn the Master, Beethoven the Pupil," circa 1926 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Notes on Haydn and Beethoven, 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      (notebook also contains essays on Sag Harbor, NY and Colonel Freemont)
    - Notes on Literature Concerning Haydn, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Notes Concerning Music, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Play- "Home," circa 1910s (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Play- Untitled, circa 1910s (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Notebook, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      (Includes 3 drafts of correspondence)
    - Notebook, circa 1927 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Notebook, circa 1920s (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Notes, circa 1920s (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Writings by Others, circa 1910s-1928, Subseries 5.2:
    - "London," by Duncan Scott Kent, circa 1910s (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - "New History of American Art," by Blackfield, circa 1928 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Artwork, circa 1920-1929, Series 6:; (Box 3; 5 folders)
  There are sketches by Britton including gallery renderings, pen and ink, and pencil; a woodcut by Britton; and pencil and crayon drawings presumably by the Britton children.
  - Woodcut Print, 1920s (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Sketch, Ink, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Sketch, Pencil, circa 1920s (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Sketch of Gallery Plans, circa 1925 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Children's Drawings, circa 1920s (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Printed Material, 1910-1982, Series 7:; (Box 4; 0.4 linear feet)
  Printed materials include publications containing writings or illustrations by Britton including Art Review International, Book Notes, Opus; clippings and articles; exhibition announcements and catalogs for Britton'w work or that contain essays written by Britton; programs for musical performances; a copy of Morocco Bound by Edwin Valentine Mitchell; and miscellany.
  This series has been partially scanned. For some exhibition catalogs and published materials, only the cover and pages with references to Britton or essays written by Britton have scanned.
  - Art Review International, 1919-1920 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Book Notes, Articles by Britton, 1926, 1920s, (partially scanned) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Book Notes, Illustrations by Britton, 1927-1928, (partially scanned) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Opus 6 and 7, circa 1922-1923 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Articles Written by or Illustrated by Britton, 1928, circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, Hartford Courant, 1910-1912 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, Art Related, 1914-1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, General, circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Exhibition Articles and Catalogs for Britton, 1917-circa 1936, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Exhibition Articles and Catalogs, Introductions by Britton, circa 1920 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Exhibition Articles and Catalogs, Connecticut Academy of Fine Arts, 1937-1938, (partially scanned) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Exhibition Articles and Catalogs, Miscellaneous, circa 1920s-1930 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Order Form for Copley, Painter of the Revolution, circa 1920 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Music Programs, 1920s-1935, (partially scanned) (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1920s-1932 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Morocco Bound, by Edwin Valentine Mitchell, 1929, (partially scanned) (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Photographs, circa 1905-1930s, Series 8:; (Box 4, OV1; 3 folders)
  There is one photograph of James Britton sitting in front of a painting of Tom Brabazon and photographs of portraits by Britton.
  This series has been partially scanned. Photographs of works of art have not been scanned.
  - Photograph of James Britton, circa 1905 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, 1908-1930s, (oversized materials housed in OV1; not scanned) (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Oversized Photographs of Works of Art, 1908-1930s, (from Box 4, F18; not scanned) (Box OV1)